<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="section.assignment-shortcuts"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" >
    <info>
        <title>Shortcuts for Common Assignment Statements</title>
    </info>

<para>
You've now no doubt wrote a statement such as the following many times:
</para>

<programlisting>
i = i + 1;
</programlisting>

<para>
This happens so frequently in Java that there are several built-in shortcuts for such statements. For instance, if we simply want to add a value to a variable (rather than replace a value in a variable), we could do so using the <code>+=</code> operator. Thus, an equivalent version of the code above is the following:
</para>

<programlisting>
i += 1;
</programlisting>

<para>
We could also add <literal>2</literal> to the value of <varname>i</varname> the same way, or any other value we want to increment it by. Similarly, we could subtract that value from <varname>i</varname>  with the <code>-=</code> operator. Each of the other arithmetic operators has a similar shortcut.
</para>
<para>
Beyond these shortcuts, it's also very common to simply add <literal>1</literal> to a variable, so there is a second shortcut that just adds <literal>1</literal>:
</para>

<programlisting>
i++;
</programlisting>

<para>
Note that this shortcut can be used to simplify the string iteration example considerably, since it uses a somewhat long variable name:
</para>

<programlisting>
<xi:include href="../../examples/code/count-l-in-hello.jsh" parse="text"/>
</programlisting>

<para>
If you've ever heard of the programming language C++ and wondered why it was named that way, now you know. Similarly, another shortcut exists for subtracting <literal>1</literal> from a variable.
</para>

<programlisting>
i--;
</programlisting>

<para> Shortcuts exist also for the other arithmetic operators. For example, the following statement will double the value held by the variable <varname>i</varname>:
<programlisting>
i *= 2;
</programlisting>
</para>

<para> This shortcut also for the concatenation operator. For example, the following statement will concatenate an exclamation mark on to the string held by the variable <varname>str</varname>:
<programlisting>
str += "!";
</programlisting>
</para>

</section>
