<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="section.repls"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" >
    <info>
        <title>Read Evaluate Print Loops (REPLs)</title>
    </info>
    
    <para>
        There are many ways to categorize programming languages. For instance, some programming languages are called <emphasis>object-oriented</emphasis>, <emphasis>functional</emphasis>, or <emphasis>statically typed</emphasis>, to name a few, and many of these categories overlap. An important category, as it relates to teaching Java to a beginning programmer, is that of <firstterm>scripting languages</firstterm>. This is important because Java has never in the past been considered one <footnote><para>Do not confuse Java with Javascript, which is an entirely different language and is indeed a scripting language.</para></footnote>, and this has led to problems when introducing it to someone who has never programmed before.
    </para>
    <para> A scripting language is one that is intended for quickly writing short, ad-hoc programs that perform a simple task, possibly only once. An important tool for working with a scripting language is a <acronym>REPL</acronym> (Read Evaluate Print Loop). A REPL allows you to run small snippets of a program, one at a time, and observe what the computer does in real time. This way the programmer can quickly react, correct errors, and experiment. This functionality is of obvious importance to a new programmer learning how to use the language. </para>
    <para> Java has long been infamous for its <emphasis>wordiness</emphasis>. That is, it took a lot of typing to say anything meaningful. For example, the first program most introductory programming books show the reader is <emphasis>Hello World!</emphasis> -- a program that simply prints these words to the screen. In Java, this required the programmer to write 5 lines of code. This degree of wordiness is essentially the opposite of the goal of a scripting language.
    </para>
    <para>This changed somewhat in September 2017 when an official REPL was added to Java, called JShell. In JShell, <emphasis>Hello World!</emphasis> is just one line:
    <figure xml:id="fig.repls.jshell">
        <title>Using the JShell REPL</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject condition="print">
                <imagedata fileref="../../tmp/jshell.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject condition="web">
                <imagedata fileref="../../tmp/jshell.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            <textobject><phrase>The Hello World! example with the JShell REPL</phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>
        JShell is an example of a command-line program run from the system terminal. You can see in the figure that the first thing JShell did after I started it up was to welcome me and indicate what version is running. After that you see the <firstterm>command prompt</firstterm>. <screen>jshell&gt;</screen>  At that prompt I typed <code>println("Hello World!");</code> which is a snippet of Java that instructs the computer to print the same message back to me. JShell read this snippet in from me (the R for read in REPL), then did as it was instructed (the E for evaluate and P for Print steps). You can see the JShell REPL complying with that command below and then returning me to the command prompt for another command (L for loop -- after each command, it waits for another, looping indefinitely).
    </para>
    
    <para>
        There are many commands you can enter at the command prompt that are not Java code snippets but are unique to using JShell. A very important one is the <code>/help</code> command. Typing in this command causes JShell to report on all the other special commands available to you. Another important command is <code>/exit</code>, which terminates JShell. We will see other commands as they become relevant in later sections. 
    </para>
</section>
