<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="section.switch-statements"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" >
    <info>
        <title>Switch Statements</title>
    </info>

<para>If each of the \textit{if} statements in an if/else chain are simply comparing some expression to one of several literal values, there is a special syntax in Java called a \textbf{switch} statement that can be used instead. Here is an example of such a scenario:
</para>
    
<example>
    <title>Switching Over Letter-Grade Characters</title>
<para>A gradebook application needs to determine the minimum grade needed for each letter grade. Letter grades will be represented with capital letter characters. The following method could be used to do the conversion:
</para>
    
<programlisting
int getMinimumGrade(char letterGrade) {
if ( letterGrade == 'A' ) {
return 90;
} else if ( letterGrade == 'B' ) {
return 80;
} else if ( letterGrade == 'C' ) {
return 70;
} else if ( letterGrade == 'D' ) {
return 60;
} else {
return 0;
}
}
></programlisting>
</example>
<para>
Switch statements begin with the switch keyword and are followed by an expression in parentheses. However, this expression does not need to be a boolean expression. Instead, it should simply produce a value that will be compared to a series of literal values. Following this, a curly brace should be opened for the body of the switch statement. 
</para><para>
The body will contain a series of \textbf{case} statements. Each case statement begins with the \textit{case} keyword, followed by the literal value that the original expression will be compared to, and then a colon. Following that will be a series of statements. Curly braces are not necessary.
</para><para>
Note that after a case statement is complete, the next case statement will be executed! Unless this is intentional, you must explicitly end the switch statement using a \textbf{break} statement. This is simply the keyword \textit{break} followed by a semicolon. Break statements are not needed if a return statement is used, since execution of the enclosing method will end at that point anyway. 
</para><para>
One last concern with switch statements is how to handle the case where the value we get back from the initial expression doesn't match any of the literal values in the cases. We could simply do nothing, or we could include a default action. These is special syntax for the latter. It looks like the other case statements, but uses the keyword \textit{default} followed by a colon instead of the usual beginning of a case statement.
</para><para>
Below is an equivalent implementation of the grade example above using a switch statement instead of an if/else chain:
</para>

<programlisting>
int getMinimumGrade(char letterGrade) {
switch(letterGrade) {
case 'A':
return 90;
case 'B':
return 80;
case 'C':
return 70;
case 'D':
return 60;
default:
return 0;
}
} 
</programlisting>
</section>

