<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="chapter.basics"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <info>
        <title>Forming Simple Programs from Statements</title>
    </info>
    
    <para>So far you've only seen small snippets of code (expressions, mostly) that accomplish something very simple. Clearly we use computers and computer programs to accomplish much more complex tasks than those we've accomplished thus far in JShell. Of course, we could build up very large and complex expressions that accomplish more complex tasks. This style of programming is called <firstterm>functional</firstterm> programming. While Java does have some support for this programing paradigm, more so Java (like most popular programming languages) is an <firstterm>imperative</firstterm> programming language. This means that Java programs, for the most part, follow a series of discrete steps, each of which updates the <firstterm>state of the program</firstterm> (perhaps the values of variables, the contents of the screen, etc). </para>
    <para>For a beginning programmer, the imperative programming paradigm will be more familiar. You've followed what amounts to an imperative program whenever you've been given a list of instructions. In fact, such an abstract list of instructions has a name in math and computer science: an algorithm. Algorithms are important to programmers because they reveal, more abstractly, how part of a program can or should work. Using algorithms doesn't depend on knowing Java or Python or any other specific language; they are written in english (or another natural language) in a way than any programmer should understand. The programmer can then use the algorithm to guide them through the process of developing the code for a portion of their program. </para>
    
    <para>This chapter will start with a closer look at algorithms. Then you will learn how to use statements (essentially a single <emphasis>step</emphasis> in an imperative program). Finally, you'll learn how to develop your own simple but complete computer programs as JShell scripts. Note that JShell scripts are not the only way to develop a complete program in Java, and in fact they are relatively new to Java, but they are the most simple way for a beginner to write their first program. We'll also take a look at Java applications in later chapters.</para>
    
    <xi:include href="../sections/algorithms/algorithms.xml"/> 
    <xi:include href="../sections/statements/statements.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="../sections/statements/declaration-statements.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="../sections/statements/assignment-statements.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="../sections/enactment/scripts.xml"/>
</chapter>