<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="section.arithmetic-expressions"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <info>
        <title>Arithmetic Expressions</title>
    </info>
    
    <para>
        Expressions can be combined together to form a larger, more complex, compound expression. To combine two expressions, a <firstterm>binary operator</firstterm> is placed between them. The operator performs some function over the values that the two expressions evaluate to (these values are called <firstterm>operands</firstterm>). For instance, + is a binary operator representing the addition operation. <literal>5</literal> is a numeric literal expression, and <code>5 + 5</code> is a more complex, compound expression using the addition operator that evaluates to the value <literal>10</literal>. 
    </para>
    
    <para>
    There are several binary arithmetic operators which work over numeric expressions in Java. Each is described below:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>+ (the addition operator)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>- (the subtraction operator)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>* (the multiplication operator)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>/ (the division operator)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>% (the modulus operator)</para>
            </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

Note that, when using the <code>/</code> operator with integers, you get back the integer quotient (rather than a floating point value). Modulus gives you the remainder when performing integer division. 
    </para>
    
    <para>
        There is also a unary operator in Java. This is an operator that works over only one operand rather than two. This is the negation operator, which, like subtraction, is represented with <code>-</code>. For instance, <literal>-5</literal> is a compound expression that is the negation of 5. 
    </para>
    
    <para>
        Also similar to algebra, note that these operators follow the same order of precedence. Multiplication and division are evaluated before addition an subtraction. For example, <code>2 * 3 + 1</code> is equal to <literal>7</literal>, not <literal>8</literal>. 
    </para>
    <para>You can also use parentheses to force a certain order of evaluation for your expressions, just as you did in algebra. For example, the expression <code>2 * (3 + 1)</code> does, in fact, evaluate to <literal>8</literal>.
    </para>
    
    <xi:include href="../../examples/averaging.xml" parse="xml"/>
    
</section>
