<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="section.conditional-expressions"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" >
    <info>
        <title>Conditional Expressions</title>
        <remark>Prerequisites: expressions</remark>
    </info>


    <para>
    In addition to conditional statements, there are also expressions that evaluate conditionally. That is, the value they evaluate to is dependent on some boolean expression.</para>

    <figure xml:id="fig.conditional-expression">
        <title>Anatomy of a Conditional Expression</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject condition="print">
                <imagedata fileref="../../tmp/conditional-expression.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject condition="web">
              <imagedata fileref="../../tmp/conditional-expression.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject><phrase>Anatomy of a Conditional Expression</phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para> Conditional expressions use two operators in conjunction: a question mark (?) and a colon (:). These operators sit between three other expressions. These five parts of a conditional expression come in this order: a boolean expression, followed by a question mark, followed by an expression that will be evaluated if the initial boolean expression is true, followed by a colon, followed by an expression that will be evaluated if the initial boolean expression is false.
    For example, consider the following conditional expression:
    </para>
<programlisting>
    5 > 10 ? 30 : 40
</programlisting>
<para>
    This expression evaluates to the value 40. Since the initial boolean expression evaluates
    to false, the expression following the colon is evaluated. The middle expression is ignored
    in this case. If we changed the comparison operator to &lt;
    the whole conditional expression would have evaluated to 30 instead.
</para>
<para>
    Here's another example that would evaluate to the maximum of two integer variables x and y:
</para>

<programlisting>
    x > y ? x : y
</programlisting>

</section>
